Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 13 -- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials 1640-1791 Mss.B.F85inventory13
American Philosophical Society
Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 13 -- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials
1640-1791
Mss.B.F85inventory13
American Philosophical Society
1.0 section
This is part of the large inventory for the Benjamin Franklin Papers (Mss B F85). For complete information concerning this collection, please view the Collection Description.
1363 items
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials
  - Miscellaneous Papers., 1642; D. 1p.; The House of Commons
    Scope and Contents note
    A bill freeing the New England Plantations from paying any custom, subsidy, taxation imposition or other duty, on goods or merchandise imported or exported.
    (Copy.)
  - to Joseph Growdon., 1670 January 27; D.S. 1p.; Courtney, Nicholas. Cornwall, England
    Bond for the sum of fifty pounds.
  - to Joseph Growdon., 1670 February 17; D.S. 1p.; Grooss, Williams. Cornwall, England
    Bond for the sum of five pounds.
  - to Lawrence Growdon., 1675 November 6; D.S. 1p.; Walker, Mary
    Receipt for one year's rent. £60.
  - to His Wife and Children., 1682 June 4; L. 4p.; Penn, William. Worminghurst
    Counsel and advice.
    Bibliography
    Printed in Janney's Life of William Penn, Philadelphia, 1852, p. 187.
  - Miscellaneous Papers., 1682 September; D. 1p.; The General Assembly of New Jersey
    Eight chapter of the Acts and Laws of the General Assembly of New Jersey in September, 1682, which gives to the town of Burlington, and to others concerned therein for educational purposes, the Island of Matininuck. The rents, issues and profits from which are to be employed for the maintaining of a school.
    (Certified copy.)
  - to Lawrence Growdon., 1684 August 28; D.S. 1p.; Morrice, Edmund
    Bond for the sum of four pounds.
  - to Law[rence] Growdon, Padstow, Cornwall [England]., 1691 March 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Coyesarne, Sampson. Bristol
    Relative to the purchase of an estate at Aushell.
  - Miscellaneous Papers., 1691 Apr. 10; D. 3p.; The Governor of Canada
    Grant of land to [Antoine] De Lamotte Cadillac.
    (In French. Copy.)
  - to Governor William Penn., 1704 Aug. 16; L. 15p.; The Freemen of Pennsylvania
    Memorial complaining of certain abuses, etc.
  - to Christopher,Baron de Graffenried., 1709 April 28; A.D.S. 2p.; Henry,Duke of Beaufort
    Commission appointing Baron de Graffenried the deputy of the Duke in that part of Carolina north and east of Cape Fear River.
  - to His Friends in Pennsylvania., 1710 April 29; L.S. 4p.; Penn, William
    Expostulates with them concerning the cause of the many troubles and oppressions he has met with from them. Informs them that he has always been willing and is now willing to make any provisions that are necessary for the prosperity of his Province, but that he cannot perceive what advantages the people will be possessed of in taking many of the provisions and executive parts of Government out of the Governor's hands and place them in an uncertain body, particularly the appointment of Judges. Thinks he does not deserve the rough treatment which he and his Secretary received from them. Appeals to them to reconsider fully what they desire of him on the one hand, and what ought to be performed to him on the other. Shall expect a reply from the next Assembly, that he may know what to rely upon.
  - to The Tuscaroras., 1711 October 8; Mem. S. and sealed. 1p.; Alexander Spotswood, Lieutenant-Governor of Virginia
    Demanding that [Christopher,] Baron of Graffenried, the chief man of the Palatines in Carolina, shall be forthwith set at liberty and sent on the Governor of Virginia, and giving notice that if they do him any violence he will revenge his blood upon every man, women and child of the nation.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1711 October 9; A.D.S. 2p.; Agreement of Christopher, Baron de Graffenried with the Tuscarora Indians and their Neighbors
    To be good friends. In wars between the English and the Indians the Baron's people to take no part and receive no harm. In cases of disagreement, complaints are to be made to the chiefest men. Freedom of Indian lands and hunting grounds.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1718-1732; 2p.; Account of the Trade of the British American Colonies
    Extracts from the journals of the Lords Commissioners for Trade and Plantations.
  - to Sir W[illiam] Keith, Governor of Pennsylvania., 1719 July 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Delafaye, Mr. Chas. Whitehall
    Sends him a copy of the Report of the Commissioners for Trade and Plantation, signifying their Excellencys approbation of what he did and their directions that he do as proposed in the Report—continue to act as Governor of Pennsylvania under his former appointment till the Proprietor and Trustees have settled their differences or until further signification of His Majesty's of their Excellencys pleasures. Report of the Board of the Trade, wherein they express their satisfaction with Mr. Keith for declining to act under his new commissions.
  - to Lawrence Growdon., 1724 October 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Hooper, John. Padstow, Cornwall, England
    Perverse winds have prevented sailing. Purchase of brandy and barley, and other business matters.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, [1725-6?]; Mem. 10p.; The Case of Sir William Keith against Springett and Hannah Penn
    Relating to the appointment of Major [Patrick] Gorden as Governor of the Province of Pennsylvania.
  - to ----- -----., 1726 November 20; A.L. 3p.; ------, -----. Pole
    Relative to rent of farm. Rough weather for sailing. Requests him to look after his wife and family.
  - to Lawrence Growdon., 1727[?] January 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Hooper, John. Padstow, Cornwall, England
    Fall in the price of corn. Hopes that he has not bought any to ship off.
  - to Lawrence Growdon, Bridgwater [England]., 1727 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Banley, J. London
    Business letter.
  - to Lawrence Growdon, Bristol., 1727 October 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Hooper, John. Padstow, Cornwall, England
    Relative to the buying, shipping and selling of wheat and barley.
  - to Lawrence Growdon, Bridgwater., 1727 October 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Hooper, John. Padstow, Cornwall, England
    Buying and selling of wheat. Accompained by a note from W[illia]m Gifford to Mr. Hooper relative to a bill coming due.
  - to Mrs. Lawrence Growdon., [1727] ----- 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Hooper, Charles. Bristol
    Informs her that his brother died of small-pox in the morning; requests her assistance as soon as possible.
  - to His Brother., 1728 March 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Growdon, Joseph Jr. Philadelphia
    Begs to be pardoned if he has used unguarded language in his last letter, which he assures him was due to youthful passions, rather than resentment; he never endeavored to influence his father against him; he knows nothing about his father's affairs or his will; he knows his brother has a right to a considerable quantity of land in Pennsylvania which has been sealed and improved or aliened and sold by his father, and whatever rights he has he will not dispute; assures him that in whatever manner their father may dispose of his estate, he will never dispute a point with him but in the kindest, most amicable and affectionate terms; and rather than be involved in unnatural discord and unhappy division will make a voluntary resignation of his own interest.
  - to Lawrence Growdon, Bridgwater [Eng.]., 1728 May 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Hooper, Jenet
    Riots of the tinners. Has heard from brother Hooper who put in at Falmouth on account of a leak. Plans for her son. Would like to apprentice him to a good business master in Bristol.
  - to Lawrence Growdon., 1728 December 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Bownas, Samuel. Bristol
    Thomas Bedel's death. Changes in the market prices.
  - to His Brother., 1730 November 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Growdon, Joseph Jr. Philadelphia
    Has just returned from Chester Court where he has been engaged in public prosecutions for the Crown. Intended to write fully but unforeseen business prevented him, and the vessel sails two days earlier. Could not manage his business so as to come over with the vessel but will be with him next spring.
  - to Wm. Bradford, 1754 October 29; Belcher, Jonathan
  - to Lawrence Growdon, Bristol., 1731 May 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Hooper, John. Padstow, Cornwall, England
    Sympathizes with him in the loss of his wife.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1731 October 25; D.S. 3p.; Alsop, Thomas. Hackinsack
    Deed of Release in favor of Edmund Kingstand, Timothy Bagley, Richard Warman, and Mary Pinhorn, of an interest in the unappropriated lands of the town of Bergen. Attested by William Provoost, Judge of the Court of Common Pleas.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1731-1734; Mem. 3p.; The Durham Iron Works
    Accounts.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1734 June 14; George II, King of Great Britain, 1683-1760
    Commission of Robert Burnett as Secretary of the Province of New Jersey.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1736-7 January 25; Diss. 1p.; -----, -----
    Experiments with various colors to show which imbibe and which repel the sun's rays.
  - to Joseph Breintnall, Philadelphia., 1736 February 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Relative to books purchased for the Library Company of Philadelphia. Accounts and drafts of answers by Joseph Breintnall.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1737, 1738 and 1745; Mem. 2p.; Census of New Jersey
  - to George II., 1740 September 2; D.S. 1p.; The House of Representatives of Pennsylvania. Philadelphia
    Complaining of the enlistment of large numbers of white servants in the army by the Lieutenant-Governor, without the consent of their masters.
  - to Lawrence Growdon., 1746 September 2; D.S. 2p.; Williams, Mary and William
    Two notices signed by each, respectively, that an agreement had been reached concerning their land.
  - to Lawrence Growdon., 1746-7 February 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Kelly, John. Hillton
    Relative to the affairs of the widow Williams and her son Richard.
  - to Colonel Henry Cary of Dungiven., 1752 August 20; A.L.S. 11p.; MacSparran, James. Narraganset, Rhode Island
    Description of the English American domain.
    Printed, in part, in Collections of Rhode Island Historical Soc., III, 131.
  - to The Rev. Paul Limwick., 1752 November 10; A.L.S. 2p.; MacSparran, James. Narraganset, New England
    Family affairs. Has been engaged in a law suit about Glebe lands about twenty-eight years and a decree has been made against him with the result of a loss of at least £600. Will go to England next spring if he can obtain his wife's consent. Vagrant, illiterate preachers swarm here.
  - to Jared Eliot, 1753 March 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Todd, Jonathan. East Guilford
    Expressing his friendship for his correspondent and asking him to present to Mr. [Benjamin] Franklin, for whom he has the greatest admiration, a few observations written by him while reading Mr. Franklin's ingenious manuscript, entitled "Physical and Meteorological Conjectures, etc."; the pleasure he derived from reading the manuscript; presents these objections merely to have them removed.
  - to William Franklin, Philadelphia., 1753 July 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, John. [Brother of Benjamin Franklin.]. Boston
    Relative to the accounts of Joseph Grant.
    General note
    1[Brother of Benjamin Franklin.]
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1753 October 30; Manuscript. 10p.; The Earl of Macclesfield
    Speech to the Royal Society on awarding the Copley Medal for that year to Benjamin Franklin. Manuscript.
    With engraved plate of the medal. 1 vol. 4to.
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin, Philadelphia., 1754 September 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Mecom, Benjamin. Antigua
    Sends by Mr. House two pots of sweet-meats; if he can get any oranges will send a keg. Describes a hurricane he witnessed on the 13th inst.; a sickly time of year; white people die much faster than usual; describes method they have of announcing the sex of the deceased, by the number of times the bell tolls.
  - to The Society Entrusted with Monies Collected for the use of Foreign Protestants in Pennsylvania., [1754.]; A.L.S. 17p.; Smith, William
    Brief remarks on the distressed and unformed state of the foreign Protestants in North America, especially in the Province of Pennsylvania, with an enquiry into the best means of supplying them with instructors and incorporating them with the English in the rising generation. A few remarks on the same subjects by the Archbishop of Canterbury.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, [1754?]; Mem. 2p.; -----, -----
    A speech reproaching the young men of the Province with love of ease and cowardice; need of armed resistance to the French and their numerous bodies of Indians; prophesies the loss of all their out-settlements.
    (Fragment.)
  - to David Hall, Philadelphia., 1755 February 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Timothy, Peter. Charles Town, S.C
    Concerning the amount of paper received and wanted and payment for the same. Will send Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin a piece of cambric by the next vessel. Begs him to send his whole account, as it stands with Mr. [Benjamin] Franklin.
  - to David Hall, Philadelphia., 1755 March 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Timothy, Peter. Charles Town, S.C
    Hopes he has received the £40 sent by Capt. Cony Edwards. Desires him to send his whole account now with Mr. [Benjamin] Franklin. Delay in getting the paper. Would have sent the money, but dollars are scarce in Carolina.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1755 May 31; D. 1p.; The Governor of the French West Indies. Port au Prince
    Leave of absence granted to Captain Guitton, of the Militia forces.
    (In French.)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1755 October 16; D.S. W[illia]m Franklin, Clerk. 1p.; The General Assembly of Pennsylvania. Philadelphia
    Resolution relative to the appointment of Richard Partridge and Robert Charles as the Agents of the Province in Great Britain.
  - to Dr. [John] Fothergill., 1755; A.L.S. 4p.; Pemberton, Israel. Philadelphia
    Has received two or three of the scandalous pamphlets which were printed in England and which were styled a "State of the Province"; 1 it alarmed all ranks to find they have some among them so desperately bent on depriving them of their liberties. Assures him that most, if not all, of the pamphlet, is false, and that it tended very much to unite rather than divide the people. When the Governors of Boston and New York were here, on their way to Annapolis to meet General Braddock, Gov. Shirley insisted in B[enjamin] Franklin going with them. He, with difficulty, undertook the journey, though he had scarce perfected the scheme, which some others had projected, for enabling the Assembly to raise money without the Governor's concurrence, and thereby demonstrating their readiness to comply with the demands of the King. The Governor [Robert Hunter Morris] mortified at the success of this scheme. After the Convention, Franklin staid behind the Governor in order to settle a post from Will's Creek to the City. He then had opportunities of frequent conference with the General and thus removed the great prejudices against the Province. The General had been informed that the Province refused to supply him with provisions, carriages, and would not open up a road from the camp to the settlements and that it was supplying the French with provisions, etc. Franklin assured him that the Assembly [of Pennsylvania] voted £5,000 to be laid out in provisions, etc., he refuted the other false charges and everything was arranged to the General's satisfaction. Franklin was unanimously thanked for this by the Assembly. The Governor's message to the Assembly. Asks him to try to obviate the disadvantages that may rise from Friends being misrepresented to the Government.
    Printed, in parts, in Works (Sparks, VII, 96, Note).
    1 A Brief State of the Province of Pennsylvania, in which the Conduct of their Assemblies for several years past is impartially examined, and the true Cause of the Continual Encroachments of the French is displayed, etc. London, R. Griffiths, 1755.
    An answer to an Invidious Pamphlet, intituled A Brief State of the Province of Pennsylvania. London, S. Bladon, 1755.
    A Brief View of the Conduct of Pennsylvania for the year 1755. London, R. Griffiths, 1756.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1755-1762; Mem. 3p.; A State of the Paper Currency Emitted in Virginia
    Date, cause, and amount of the different emissions.
  - to Richard Partridge., 1756 January 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Barrington, Lord. Cavendish Square, London
    The bill concerning which they had corresponded, will be solely confined to a regiment proposed to be raised in America; the papers he received contain the substance of everything that is intended to be inserted in the Act.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin., 1756 January 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Weyman, William. New York
    Asks credit for the enclosed. Requests her to send him eighteen or twenty reams of newspaper by boat and when O'Brien sails to put on board as much more of news and brown paper as she can spare.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1756 January; D.S. 4p.; Franklin, John. Boston
    His will.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1756 February 26; Mem. 2p.; Proceedings before the Lords of Trade. London
    Referring to a petition by sundry inhabitants of Pennsylvania to the Assembly of that Province, complaining of the defenceless state of he Province and of the mischief done by the Indians.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1756, April 19-1765, May 11; Mem. 10p.; Minutes of Several Meetings with the Indians
    Philadelphia and Fort Pitt.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1756 May 8; Diss. 6p.; The Academy of Sciences of Paris
    Report made by a commission appointed to examine a project for the establishment of a foundry or factory for making a new kind of cannon or ordnance, by a secret process invented by M. Hannoteau, who claimed the new gun would be lighter, more durable and less costly than the old style cannon. The conclusions of the report are favorable to the project and to the claims of the inventor.
  - to Richard Partridge., 1756 August 14; L.S. 1p.; Paris, Ferdinand John. London
    He presented to His Majesty in Council, two Acts of Assembly passed in Pennsylvania. (1) An Act for dispersing the inhabitants of Nova Scotia imported into this Province, into the several counties of Philadelphia, Bucks, Chester and Lancaster, and make provisions for the same. (2) An Act for regulating the officers and soldiers commissioned and raised by the Governor for the defence of this Province.
  - to A Committee Appointed by the Meeting for Pennsylvania and New Jersey., 1756 August 19; D. 2p.; The Proprietors of the Province of Pennsylvania
    First thoughts of an answer relative to the Lower County's Militia Act of the Assembly.
  - to the Governor of Pennsylvania [William Denny]., 1756 December 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Bouquet, Lt. Col. Henry. Philadelphia
    Demanding immediate quarters for Gen. [Daniel] Webb, his two aides-de-camp and one battalion of the Royal American Regiment, also a hospital capable of holding 100 sick.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1757 January 4 and 8; D.S. Abel James, Clerk. 2p.; Minutes of the Friendly Association for Regaining and Preserving Peace with the Indians by Pacific Measures. at Alexander Seaton's
  - to Rich[ar]d Partridge, Tho[ma]s Jackson, and John Fothergill., 1757 January 10; L.S. 3p.; Pemberton, Israel and James. Philadelphia
    Proposed friendly conference with the Indians on the Northern frontiers. The Indians they believe will continue peaceable if they are treated with justice and candor. George Croghan has been commissioned to endeavor, with the same measures which succeeded with the Delawares on the Susquehanna, to draw the Ohio Indians to a Conference. Friends freely subscribed a fund to be applied for the obtaining of peace. Due care has been taken on the part of the Proprietors to purchase the land from the Indians and to satisfy them for their titles, etc. Complains of the treatment they received when they offered to contribute towards the expense of regulating the matter after it had been imprudently conducted. The Assembly is preparing a bill for raising £100,000 and a militia bill.
  - to William Callender and Israel Pemberton., 1757 January 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Peters, Richard. Philadelphia
    Laid their application, with regard to the inspection of the Council books, before the Governor; the transacting of business with the Indians is a matter so entirely pertaining to the Governor that he cannot permit any one except those who are empowered by the King or himself to mediate with the affairs of that people. Should, however, anything be contained in the minutes that concerns the rights or property of any person, such person, by a proper application, may be furnished with a copy.
  - [, D. 1p.; Wheatley, Henry
    Extract from his will relative to £100 left to Benjamin Franklin trust for John Cole.
  - to William Franklin. New York., 1757 [June?]; A.L.S. 3p.; Thomson, Charles. New York
    Indian affairs. Governor [Denny] to make a tour of the frontier forts. [William] Pitt [first Earl of Chatham]'s letter to the Governor. Electrical apparatus to be purchased for the [American Philosophical] Society.
  - to Geo[rge] Croghan.Easton, Pa., 1757 July 25; L. 4p.; -----, -----
    Relative to the troubles they had with the Indians of Pennsylvania about lands purchased from their ancestors.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1757; Mem. 1p.; William Franklin's Accounts
  - to William Franklin., 1758 January 2; A.L.S. 4p.; Thomson, Charles. Philadelphia
    Indian affairs. Pennsylvania politics. Death of William Parsons, of Northampton. Marriage of [William] Moore. Sends respects to Mr. [Benjamin] Franklin.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin., 1758 January 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Mecom, Benjamin. Boston
    Received a letter from his brother Ebenezer, the baker, with the money for the bolting cloth, and according to her instructions he sent her the money, after paying his brother John for the spoons she presented them with. Showed Cousin [Jonathan] Williams [Sr.] her letter concerning Mr. [Joseph] Dowse, which he does not understand; asks her to send the amount on a slip of paper, he will deliver it, receive the money and send it to her. Report that Uncle [Benjamin] Franklin was further promoted at home.
  - to William Franklin., 1758 March 12-16; A.L.S. 4p.; Thomson, Charles
    Has had no answer to his letters. Indian affairs and Pennsylvania politics.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin., 1758 April 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Mecom, Benjamin. Boston
    Acknowledges the receipt of three parcels of papers. Shall be glad if she can replace the ten reams he delivered to [Samuel] Kneeland as he is still about an edition of the psalter and has not enough paper Sorry he cannot pay her now, but promises to send her some money when the pslater is finished. Asks for the price of the smallest and plainest of the Pennsylvania fire places, as he will need one for his office during the winter.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1758 April 12, 13; D, 13p.; Minutes of Conferences between the Government of Pennsylvania and Teedyuscung, King of the Delawares
  - to Richard Partridge., 1758 July 6; L.S. 1p.; Paris, Ferdinand John. Surry Street
    The Proprietaries of Pennsylvania were informed that the papers relating to the charge made by the Indian Teedyuskung were to be laid before his Majesty and his Ministers; it cannot be discovered that the papers were brought in, and he desires to be informed whether the papers have arrived, and whether they are to or when they will be presented to his Majesty.
  - to William Callender., 1758 October 31; L.S. 1p.; Spicer, Jacob. Philadelphia